Guide to the Vago Family Papers TAM.847
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Vago Family Papers
1933-1985
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Vago, Oscar J.
Vago Family
TAM.847
0.44 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
Oscar J. Vago was a Hungarian-born structural and civil engineer who became embroiled in the U.S. government's espionage investigations as the Cold War unfolded at the close of World War II. Vago briefly had a professional partnership with Abraham Brothman. Brothman owned a chemical engineering company in Long Island City that employed Harry Gold, who later declared himself an atomic spy and was a key witness against Julius and Ethel Rosenberg. In 1950, Vago was questioned by the FBI and indicted for perjury. In the media Vago was portrayed as a missing link in the so-called Russian atom spy ring, and—-because of his Hungarian Jewish background/heritage—-was treated with suspicion in the media and courtroom. The Vago Family Papers (1933-1985) document the lives of the Vago Family (Oscar Vago and his wife Claire Vago, and their two children), the 1950 court case against Oscar Vago, and Vago's business relationship with Abraham Brothman. Materials include family memoirs, legal records, correspondence, and FOIA documents.
Scope and Contents
The Vago Family Papers (1933-1985) document the lives of the Vago Family (Oscar Vago and his wife Claire Vago, and their two children), a 1950 court case against Oscar Vago, and Vago's business relationship with Abraham Brothman. Materials include family memoirs; legal records such as court transcripts, the judge's sentencing document, and discharge papers; and correspondence between Oscar and Claire while he was incarcerated. Memoirs, written by both Claire and Oscar Vago, describe their ancestors, growing up Jewish in Hungary and Germany, respectively, and coming to America. The memoirs and correspondence between Oscar and Claire reflect the impact of Oscar's incarceration on the family and their states of mind during this time. The collection also includes records of the dissolution of Vago's business partnership with Brothman, Vago's 1948 lawsuit against Brothman, pamphlets issued by the Federation of Architects and Engineers (CIO), documents regarding the New York State Regents suspension of Vago's professional engineering license, and a 1975 Freedom of Information Act request and response. All of these materials document the effects of the Cold War on American Jews and the general anti-Communist sentiment at the time.
Biographical Note
Oscar J. Vago was a Hungarian-born structural and civil engineer who became embroiled in the U.S. government's espionage investigations as the Cold War unfolded at the close of World War II. Vago briefly had a professional partnership with Abraham Brothman. Brothman owned a chemical engineering company in Long Island City that employed Harry Gold, who later declared himself an atomic spy and was a key witness against Julius and Ethel Rosenberg. Brothman was convicted in 1950 of conspiracy to impede a grand jury investigation and for conspiring with his secretary Miriam Moskowitz and Harry Gold to obstruct justice.
Vago, who was Jewish, had emigrated from Hungary to the U.S. in 1925 with a student visa, but overstayed the visa's time limit. After he married Hungarian emigre Claire Weiszmann, who became a U.S. citizen, the couple visited Hungary in 1932-1933 and Vago was able to return to the U.S. under an immigrant visa. He subsequently became a U.S. citizen. In 1950 he was questioned by the FBI and then subpoenaed to testify before a grand jury. Questioned, without an attorney present, about the date of his immigration to the U.S., he gave the later date. After consulting an attorney, he returned to the grand jury one week later and asked to correct his earlier testimony. His request was denied. In September 1950 he was indicted for perjury with a $50,000 bail. He was imprisoned at the Federal House of Detention in New York City until January 1951, when his family was able to get the bail reduced and raise the necessary funds. In the media Vago was portrayed as a missing link in the so-called Russian atom spy ring, and—-because of his Hungarian Jewish background/heritage—-was treated with suspicion in the media and courtroom. Finally, in June 1952, Vago was declared guilty by judge Sylvester Ryan following a brief trial without a jury. Ryan sentenced him to three years' probation, in a highly political sentencing statement. He noted that Vago had no ill intent in misstating the date of his arrival in the U.S., but based his guilty verdict on Vago's assumed Communist affiliation and Hungarian heritage.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sue Webb, daughter of Oscar and Claire Vago, on March 6, 2025. The accession number associated with this gift is 2025.021.
Civil engineers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Trials (Espionage) -- United States.; Political prisoners.; Indictments (legal documents).; Cold War.; Anti-communist movements -- United States.
- New York State Regents -- Revocation of Professional Engineering License, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Vago v. A. Brothman Associates, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- U.S. v. Vago, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Mosaics of My Life" by Claire Vago, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "My Story" #3 by Oscar Vago, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Oscar Vago Employment History -- Including War Department, 1933-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence between Oscar and Claire During Incarceration, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Prison Newsletters, Menus, and Floorplans, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Federation of Architects and Engineers Union -- Correspondence and Pamphlets, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- FOIA Documents and Request, 1951-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)